James G. Riggs Papers
State University of New York at Oswego
James G. Riggs Papers
1915-1936
The James G. Riggs Papers collection contains materials collected by members of SUNY Oswego about the third principal of the Oswego Normal School from 1913 to 1933. During his tenure as principal James Riggs expanded the industrial arts program and opened Park Hall, added more land to the current college location, and guided the school through World War 1, the outbreak of Influenza Epidemic of 1919, and the onset of the Great Depression.
1 cubic foot
Riggs, James G.
State University of New York at Oswego Penfield Library 7060 State Route 104 Oswego, New York 13126-3599
2005.040.0001
Collection is open to the public.
James G. Riggs was born in Dexter, New York on May 21, 1861. His parents were Edwin Starr Riggs and Cynthia A. Hardy Riggs. He graduated from Potsdam Normal School. He received a Bachelor of Arts degree in 1888 and later a Master of Arts degree from Amherst College.
From 1891 - 1893 he was the principal of Watertown (New York) High School. He then was superintendent of schools in Plattsburg, New York for seven years. From there he taught at a private school in Dobbs Ferry for five years. In 1905 he became superintendent of schools in Orange, New Jersey until his move to Oswego, New York in 1911 to become the third principal of Oswego Normal School. He remained at Oswego until his retirement in 1933
Among his interests and activities are the following: President of the New York State Historical Society. President of the Oswego Historical Society. President of the District Historical Society. Honorary degree of Doctor of Pedagogy from Albany Teachers' College. Member of the Board of Visitors of Rome State School. Elder of Grace Presbyterian Church, Oswego, New York. Member of the Fortnightly Club, Oswego, New York. Member of Lake Placid Club. Member of Theta Delta Chi fraternity. Member of University Travel Study Club, 225 South State Street, Syracuse, New York.
After his retirement, Dr. & Mrs. Riggs (May Jones Riggs) went on a world tour. Detailed letters were published in the Oswego Palladium-Times. (Photocopies and transcripts of some of those newspaper clippings are included.)
Sheldon, E. A. (Edward Austin), 1823-1897; State University College (Oswego, N.Y.); Swetman, Ralph Waldo, 1886-1957; Bagley, William C. (William Chandler), 1874-1946; Culkin, Francis D., 1874-1943; Graves, Frank Pierrepont, 1869-1956; Dearborn, Ned H. (Ned Harland), 1893-1962; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945; State Teachers College at Oswego (Oswego, N.Y.); College presidents; Psi Phi Fraternity; Sheldon Hall; Bennett, Charles; Brinkerhoff, George J.; Brock, Arthur; Brubacher, A. R.; Cochrane, John F.; Cocknell, Edward; Cousins, Minnie C.; Cribben, Leo T.; Early, James M.; Farnham, Amos W.; Ferry, Frederick C.; Ganders, Harry S.; Hart, Isabelle K.; Hauler, Arthur; Holmes, Henry W.; Johnson, Robert Underwood, 1853-1937; Jordan, Riverda H.; Karcher, Harry M.; Kellas, Eliza; Kingsford, Thomas; Libby, Ransom; Lockwood, Stephen R.; Lyons, Bertha L.; Mollison, Gilbert; Morgan, Joy Elmer; Park, John W.; Ripley, Addie; Rudolph, Jay; Schneider, Frank E.; Scoville, Wadsor M.; Smith, Payson; Steele, Robert M.; Van Oot, Benjamin H.; Whitney, Rich Dean; Withers, John W.; Woolley, Mary E.
Dr. Riggs papers include newspaper clippings, obituaries and correspondence. Subjects include Oswego Normal School, Hall of Fame nomination of Dr. Edward Austin Sheldon and world tour correspondence.
- Amos W. Farnham, 1917 - 1918 (Box-folder 01-01)
  December 1917. "My Ship in Port". 2-page handwritten poem signed Amos W. Farnham, Daytona, Florida. December 1917. "Jack's Enlisted". 2-page handwritten poem signed Amos W. Farnham, Daytona, Fla. June 5, 1918. "My Service Flag. (A Mother's Prayer)" 1-page handwritten poem signed Amos W. Farnham. June 7, 1918. 1-page handwritten letter to Dr. Riggs asking his opinion of the attached poem. "Memorial Day". 3-page handwritten poem. June 16, 1918. 1-page handwritten letter to Dr. Riggs with attached poems. "What Puzzled Need". 1-page handwritten poem. "To Robert Bunyan McCully. In Memory of his 72nd Birthday, September 2, 1916". 3-page handwritten poem. 1 typewritten page with two poems. "My Little Namesake" and "In a Nutshell".
- Hall of Fame Nomination - Edward Austin Sheldon, January 11, 1935 - March 6, 1935 (Box-folder 01-02)
  2-page handwritten list of 21 names. 17 incoming and outgoing letters between Dr. Riggs and many of the names on the aforementioned list concerning the nomination of Dr. Edward Austin Sheldon to the Hall of Fame at New York University. Correspondents include William C. Bagley (Columbia University), Robert A. Downey, Frank Pierrepont Graves, Dr. Monroe (Columbia University), Ned H. Dearborn (New York University), J. A. Pitman (President, State Teachers College at Salem, Massachusetts), Dr. Robert Underwood Johnson, D. B. Waldo (Western State Teachers College, Kalamazoo, Michigan), Charles H. Judd (University of Chicago), Payson Smith (Commissioner of Education, Boston, Massachusetts), J. W. Crabtree (National Education Association), and H.L. Smith (Dean, Indiana University).
- Hall of Fame Nomination - Edward Austin Sheldon, March 7, 1935 - March 15, 1935 (Box-folder 01-03)
  12 typed and handwritten incoming and outgoing letters and postcards concerning the nomination of Dr. Edward Austin Sheldon to the Hall of Fame at New York University. Correspondents include: Dr. William C. Bagley (Columbia University), Bertha Lyons (Assistant to Director Robert Underwood Johnson, New York University), Dr. Frank P. Graves (Commissioner of Education, Albany, New York), Dr. Ned H. Dearborn (New York University), Dr. Joy Elmer Morgan (Editor, National Education Association Journal), Minnie Cousins, and Director Robert Underwood Johnson.
- Hall of Fame Nomination - Edward Austin Sheldon, March 16, 1935 - November 12, 1935 (Box-folder 01-04)
  20 typed and handwritten incoming and outgoing letters and postcards regarding the nomination of Dr. Edward Austin Sheldon's nomination to the Hall of Fame at New York University. Correspondents include: William C. Bagley (Columbia University), Dr. Joy Elmer Morgan (National Education Offices), Henry W. Holmes (Harvard University), Francis D. Culkin (House of Representatives, Washington, D.C.), Ned H. Dearborn (New York University), Bertha L. Lyons (Assistant to Director Robert Underwood Johnson, New York University), Riverda H. Jordan (Cornell University), Harry S. Ganders (Dean, Syracuse University), Frederick C. Ferry (President, Hamilton College), A. R. Brubacher (President, New York State College for Teachers), B. H. Van Oot (State Supervisor of Trade and Industrial Education, Richmond, Virginia), Mary E. Woolley (Mount Holyoke College), John W. Withers (Dean, New York University School of Education), Robert M. Steele, Stephen R. Lockwood, Charles Bennett (The Manual Arts Press, Peoria, Illinois), Eliza Kellas (Emma Willard School, Troy, New York), and Dr. Ralph Swetman.
- Hall of Fame Nomination - Edward Austin Sheldon, 1933 - 1935 (Box-folder 01-05)
  "State Scholarships for Teachers in Training" by James G. Riggs. 14 pages. n.d. 3 1/8" x 5 3/4" paper bound booklet. "Handbook of The Hall of Fame". New York University. July, 1933. Published by The Hall of Fame, Robert Underwood Johnson, Director. 61 pages. 4 1/4" x 6 3/4" paper bound booklet. Hall of Fame of New York University, Eight Quinquennial Election, 1935, Form of Proposal for Candidates. 1 sheet. Form is on front, reverse is list of names in the Hall of Fame. "References to Edward Austin Sheldon and to His Educational Work at the Oswego Normal and Training School, Oswego, N.Y." 1 typed page + 2nd page with 3 lines.
- Miscellany, 1930 - 1936 (Box-folder 01-06)
  Letter from Governor Franklin D. Roosevelt to John M. Gill concerning budget appropriation for Oswego Normal School addition. January 13, 1930. "On the Passing of Dr. James G. Riggs By the Faculty". 1-page typed announcement signed The Committee, Oswego Normal School, February 24, 1936. Agenda for Riggs Memorial Assembly. February 25, 1936. 1 typed page. Ticket for invitation to the faculty from Mr. & Mrs. James G. Riggs. 4" x 2 3/4" "To the Faculty: With Christmas Greetings, James G. Riggs" is handwritten at the top of the page with the following typed message: "For the convenience of all will you pass the 'Shackled Youth' after two days to the next teacher on the list: " A list of 30 faculty members is typed below.
- Obituaries - James G. Riggs, February, 1936 (Box-folder 01-07)
  February 20, 1936 newspaper clipping. Includes photocopy. Uncited. "Tributes Paid to Dr. Riggs at Normal School". Newspaper clipping. February 25, 1936. Oswego Palladium-Times. Includes photocopy. February 1936. Dr. James G. Riggs obituary. Uncited. Includes photocopy. "Funerals. Dr. James G. Riggs". February 1936. Includes photocopy. 1-page typed invitation suggesting the building of Sheldon Hall (not the Sheldon Hall of 2005 - which during Dr. Riggs' time was called Oswego Normal School) as a home for students. Signed by James G. Riggs. n.d.
- Ephemera, 1920 (Box-folder 01-08)
  "The University of the State of New York Certificate of Best Wishes to Principal James G. Riggs". In the center is a photograph of a man signing a document and a second man standing to the right. Under the photo is the following message: "I have signed a hundred thousand certificates, diplomas, licenses, etc., during the past seven years, under the name of this 'mystical university' which we have served together, but before I go, I sign (Aaron witnessing) and give to you this Special Certificate of my lasting Best Wishes to you". Christmas 1920. There is a signature on the lower right. Unsure of name.
- Letter to Psi Phi boys, 1930 (Box-folder 01-09)
  One photographed copy and one photocopy of a letter from Dr. James G. Riggs to Psi Phi. A handwritten note on the back of the photograph, "Letter written by Principal Riggs to Psi Phi boys requesting that they return purloined signs. 1930".
- Roosevelt letter, June 13, 1932 (Box-folder 01-10)
  1 typed letter to Mr. Riggs from Governor Franklin D. Roosevelt in response to invitation to Industrial Arts building dedication. Original and photocopy.
- Board of Regents, 1913 - 1932 (Box-folder 01-11)
  "Regents Minutes Referring to Industrial Teachers Scholarships". Signed at top of page by Arthur J. Dudley and Roy G. Fales. Two entries dated 1920 and 1921. Typed. 1 page. "Regents Minutes Referring to Buffalo State Normal School, 1913 - 1918". Signed at top of page by Roy G. Fales. 4 typed pages. "Regents Minutes Referring to Oswego State Normal School, 1913 - 1932". Signed at top of page by Arthur J. Dudley and Roy G. Fales. Includes entries concering Dr. James G. Riggs, Dr. Isaac B. Poucher, James M. Early, Elliott Mott, Thomas P. Kinsford, Ransom I. Libby, Jay D. Rudolph, George J. Brinkerhoff, Arthur L. Brock, John Cochrane, Edward Cockell, John W. Park, John Cochrane, Wadsor M. Scoville, Rich Dean Whitney, Ned Harland Dearborn, Harry M. Karcher, Arthur Hauler, the Sheldon statue, Frank E. Schneider, Sheldon Hall, Inc., and Leo T. Cribben. 4 typed pages.
- James G. Riggs, 1936 (Box-folder 01-12)
  "Tributes Paid to Dr. Riggs at Normal School". 1936 newspaper clipping. Uncited. "Obituary. Dr. James G. Riggs". 1936 newspaper clipping. Uncited. Includes photocopies.
- Newspaper clippings, February, 1936 (Box-folder 01-13)
  8 clippings are arranged chronologically. "Normal School Closes In Tribute for Riggs; Funeral Is Saturday". Original and photocopy. "In Memory. Tribute To Dr. Riggs Paid by Mrs. Herbert Stanley Smith". Original, photocopy and transcription. "Tributes Paid To Dr. Riggs At Normal School. Dr. Walter D. Cavert Principal Speaker at Memorial Services". Original and 7-page transcript. "Obituary. Dr. James G. Riggs". Original, photocopy and transcript. "Faculty Resolutions". Original and photocopy. "Members Service. For Dr. James G. Riggs at Normal School Tuesday Morning". Original and photocopy. "Dr. Riggs' Funeral. Friends Invited to Services at Home on Saturday Afternoon". Original and photocopy. "Dr. James G. Riggs". Original and photocopy.
- Newspaper clippings, August, 1933 - July, 1934 (Box-folder 01-14)
  14 clippings are arranged chronologically. "Present Gift To Dr. Riggs. Given Barometer By Members of Summer School Faculty". Original and transcript. "Dinner for Dr. Riggs". Original and photocopy. "Leave For World Tour. Dr. and Mrs. Riggs Went to New York Tuesday Morning". Original and transcipt. "Faculty Hears From Dr. Riggs. Receives Letters Written On Steamer Near Canal Zone. Original and transcript. "Finds Graduates From Normal In Hawaiian Group. Dr. Riggs, In Brief Visit, Learns How Much Oswego Methods Accomplished". Original, photocopy and transcript. "Dr. Riggs Tells of Beauty Spots in California. Letter Mailed From Honolulu Where He Met Normal Graduates". Original, photocopy and transcript. "Dr. Riggs Sends Interesting Letter on Visit to Island Empire". Photocopy and transcript. "Japan's Temples Use Telephones Dr. Riggs Finds. Former Normal Principal Visit Island Empire of the Rising Sun". Original and photocopy. "Oswego Trained Teachers Active In Japan Field. Dr. Riggs Sends Interesting Letter on Visit to Island Empire". Original, photocopy and transcription. "Greetings From Mrs. J. G. Riggs Sent From China. Written to Winter Club Members In Connection With 50th Anniversary Of Organization". Original, photocopy and transcript. January 15, 1934. "Riggs Touring, Enjoys Ceylon's Spicy Breezes. Dr. Riggs Writes of Trip About Island In Cadillac Car". Original, photocopy and transcript. March 2, 1934. "Riggs Dined Off Syracuse China On Eastern Ocean. Thousand Island Dressing Was Also Served With Their Salad". Original, photocopy and transcript. February 20, 1934. "Riggses To Spend Their Summer In English Cottage. Former Normal Principal, On World Tour, Writes Another Intesting Letter". Original, photocopy and transcript. "To Return In August. Dr. and Mrs. Riggs Will Sail from England Next Month". Original and photocopy.
- Miscellaneous, 1915 - 1933 (Box-folder 01-15)
  Photocopies of 6 index from the Dorothy Rogers Papers ( 50/3/31). Biographical information on Dr. James G. Riggs. Newspaper clippings: * Obituary of Mrs. Elizabeth Spicer Riggs. February 6, 1915. * Steamer accident. May 30, 1923. * New York Historical Society meeting. September 17, 1924. * "Normal Entrance Being Cleared by Snow Tractor". February 5, 1925. * "Alumni Breakfast". February 20, 1932. * "Normal Bids Are Going to Albany for Final Choice". April 13, 1932. * "Plan New Camp Site at Normal". August 8, 1933. Citations of Dr. Riggs entry in "Who Was Who in America" and "Dictionary of North American Authors Deceassed before 1950". Citations for three publications: "The Vicar of Wakefield: a tale supposed to be written by himself"' by Oliver Goldsmith. Editor, James Gilbert Riggs. Boston: Sibley & Ducker, 1896. "Sesames and lilies; three lectures" by John Ruskin. Editor, James Gilbert Riggs. Boston: Sibley & Ducker, 1900. "Training of teachers for special classes" by James Gilbert Riggs. National Education Association of the United States. Journal of Proceedings and addresses, 1916. Pages 884 - 886. "Hello Doctor; a brief biography of Charles Bernstein, M.D." by James Gilbert Riggs. East Aurora, N.Y., 1936.